Guide to the Walnut Creek Shareware Collection M2253
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Walnut Creek shareware collection
1993-2006
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Scott, Jason
M2253
2 Linear Feet: 2 cartons
Collection of shareware on optical disc, all distributed by the company Walnut Creek and its successors.
Content Description
This is a collection of optical discs distributed by Walnut Creek software and its successor companies from roughly 1992 to 2006. The software was donated by the Internet Archive via Jason Scott, and likely duplicates titles in their Shareware CD Collection (https://archive.org/details/cdbbsarchive). The optical discs all come in jewel cases; there are approximately 801 cases, and each contains anywhere from 1 to 6 discs.
About half of the collection is composed of shareware anthologies. Discs often contain an amalgamation of games, fonts, pictures, utilities (i.e. diagnostic programs), and productivity suites (i.e. word processors). The user was expected to pay for the full experience of a shareware program if they liked it, and likely wouldn't have access to the full functionality until they paid. Some of the discs present are freeware, which don’t require a fee, or fully-functional programs that were presumably paid for upfront (like Applixware Office for FreeBSD).
Other discs in the collection allow the user access to free operating systems - largely centered around Unix and the “Unix-like” Linux and FreeBSD paradigms. Major examples in this collection include Berkeley’s FreeBSD series, LINUX Redhat, TurboLinux, Slackware Linux, and so on.
Walnut Creek thrived in an era where people couldn’t get online to find shareware quickly. Having virtual “shopping malls” of sorts at one’s fingertips made these discs popular. The company became part of BSDI (the company behind BSD) in 2000, Said company was then purchased by Wind River Systems, ending with FreeBSD being spun off as FreeBSD Mall. All disks prior to 2000 are published by Walnut Creek. During this time period the publishers of the discs transition from Walnut Creek to BSDI, then joint publishing between BSDI and Wind River, and finally publishing by BSDMall in the most recent artifacts.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Digital media are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to digital use copies.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Given to Stanford University, Special Collections by Jason Scott of the Internet Archive.
Scott, Jason
- Source Code CDROM (MSDOS/Unix/Windows), Dec. 1993 (Box 1)
- Usenet Source Code Vol. 1 (DOS/Unix), Apr. 1996 (Box 1)
- Turbo User Group Vol. 2 (DOS/Windows), Jul. 1996 (Box 1)
- Ultra Mac-Games (Mac), May 1994 (Box 1)
- Plug-and-Play Linux (Linux), Nov. 1994 (Box 1)
- Linux Games (Linux), Jul. 1999 (Box 1)
- LINUX Redhat 5.0 (Linux), Feb. 1998 (Box 1)
- LINUX Redhat 5.1 (Linux), Feb. 1998 (Box 1)
- LINUX Red Hat 6.0 (Linux), Jun. 1999 (Box 1)
- X11R6 CDROM (Unix), Jul. 1994 (Box 1)
- GIFs Galore CDROM (All platforms available in 1993), Sep. 1993 (Box 1)
- Fractal Frenzy: Visions of Chaos Volume 1 (PC/Mac), Dec. 1993 (Box 1)
- UNIX Freeware (Unix), Oct. 1998 (Box 1)
- X11R6 CDROM (Unix), Apr. 1995 (Box 1)
- GIFs Galore CDROM (All platforms available in 1992), Aug. 1992 (Box 1)
- X11R6 CDROM (Unix), Oct. 1995 (Box 1)
- TurboLinux 2.0 (Linux), Aug. 1998 (Box 1)
- Linux Toolkit (Linux), Jul. 1999 (Box 1)
- Linux Web Tools (Linux), Feb. 1999 (Box 1)
- Business Apps for Linux (Linux), Jul. 1999 (Box 1)
- Turbo Business Apps for Linux v. 2 (Linux), 1998 (Box 1)
- Ada CDROM (DOS, Unix), Jul. 1994 (Box 1)
- Ada (DOS, Unix), Jun. 1995 (Box 1)
- Ada (DOS, Unix) (Special Edition for the 1996 ACM Computing Week Conference and the 1996 DoD Software Technology Conference!), Feb. 1996 (Box 1)
- Ada Two Disc Set! (A Special Edition for the Tri-Ada '97 and Ada-Belgium '97 Conferences (Windows 95/NT, MSDOS, UNIX, HTML), Nov. 1997 (Box 1)
  - Applixware Office for FreeBSD (Unix), Nov. 1999 (Box 1)
  - FreeBSD Toolkit- Six Disc Set! (Unix), May 1999 (Box 1)
  - FreeBSD Toolkit - Six Disc Set! (Unix), Jun. 2000 (Box 1)
  - FreeBSD Toolkit- Six Disc Set! (Unix), Feb. 2001 (Box 1)
  - Hobbes OS/2 (OS/2), Oct. 1993 (Box 1)
  - Hobbes OS/2 (OS/2), Feb. 1994 (Box 1)
  - Hobbes OS/2 Archived (OS/2), Aug. 1994 (Box 1)
  - Ready-to-Run Hobbes OS/2 (OS/2), Nov. 1994 (Box 1)
  - Hobbes Archived OS/2 (OS/2), Mar. 1995 (Box 1)
  - Hobbes OS/2 Archived (OS/2), Dec. 1995 (Box 1)
  - Hobbes OS/2 Archived (OS/2) (German), Jun. 1996 (Box 1)
  - Hobbes OS/2 (OS/2), Apr. 1998 (Box 1)
  - Linux Slackware (Unix), Mar. 1995 (Box 1)
  - Slackware Linux 3.0 (Unix), Oct. 1995 (Box 1)
  - Slackware Linux 3.0 (Unix) (Japanese), Oct. 1995 (Box 1)
  - Linux Slackware 96 - Four Disc Set + 36-pg Installation Guide! (Unix), Aug. 1996 (Box 1)
  - Slackware Linux 4.0 - Four Disc Set! KDE Graphical Desktop Environment (Linux), Jun. 1999 (Box 1)
  - Slackware Linux 4.0 - Four Disc Set! KDE Graphical Desktop Environment (Linux), Jun. 1999 (Box 1)
  - Slackware Linux 7 (Linux), Nov. 1999 (Box 1)
  - Slackware Linux 7.1 - Four Disc Set! GNOME & KDE Graphical Environments, Jul. 2000 (Box 1)
- La Coleccion (DOS, Windows, OS/2), Jun. 1993 (Box 1)
- La Coleccion (OS/2, DOS, Windows), Mar. 1996 (Box 1)
- Music Workshop CDROM (Windows), Jan. 1995 (Box 1)
- Audio Toolkit (Mac, MSDOS, Unix, Windows 95/NT), Sept. 1997 (Box 1)
- Jolt! Developer's Tookit for Java (Windows 95/NT, Unix, Mac, HTML), Oct. 1997 (Box 1)
- Linux Toolkit- 6 Disc Set! Tools, Sources, Utilities (Linux), Jan. 1999 (Box 1)
- Applixware Office for FreeBSD, Nov. 1999 (Box 1)
- FreeBSD Toolkit - Six Disc Set! (Unix), May 1999 (Box 1)
- FreeBSD Toolkit - Six Disc Set! (Unix), Jun. 2000 (Box 1)
- FreeBSD Toolkit - Six Disc Set! (Unix), Feb. 2001 (Box 1)
- Hobbes OS/2 (OS/2), Oct. 1993 (Box 1)
- Hobbes OS/2 (OS/2), Feb. 1994 (Box 1)
- Hobbes OS/2 Archived (OS/2), Aug. 1994 (Box 1)
- Ready-to-Run Hobbes OS/2 (OS/2), Nov. 1994 (Box 1)
- Hobbes Archived OS/2 (OS/2), Mar. 1995 (Box 1)
- Hobbes OS/2 Archived (OS/2), Dec. 1995 (Box 1)
- Hobbes OS/2 Archiviert (OS/2) (German), Jun. 1996 (Box 1)
- Hobbes OS/2 (OS/2), Apr. 1998 (Box 1)
- Linux Slackware (Unix), Mar. 1995 (Box 1)
- Slackware Linux 3.0 (Unix), Oct. 1995 (Box 1)
- Slackware Linux 3.0 (Unix) (Japanese), Oct. 1995 (Box 1)
- Linux Slackware 96 - Four Disc Set + 36-pg Installation Guide! (Unix), Oct. 1996 (Box 1)
- Slackware Linux 4.0 - Four Disc Set! KDE Graphical Desktop Environment (Linux), Jun. 1999 (Box 1)
- Slackware Linux 4.0 - Four Disc Set! KDE Graphical Desktop Environment (Linux), Jun. 1999 (Box 1)
- Slackware Linux 7 (Linux), Nov. 1999 (Box 1)
- Slackware Linux 7.1 - GNOME & KDE Graphical Environments (Linux), Jul. 2000 (Box 1)
- FreeBSD 2.0 (Unix), Jan. 1994 (Box 2)
- FreeBSD 2.0.5 (Unix), Jun. 1995 (Box 2)
- FreeBSD 2.1 (Unix), Jan. 1996 (Box 2)
- FreeBSD 2.2.5 - Four Disc Set! Rock-stable Performance (Unix), Nov. 1997 (Box 2)
- FreeBSD 2.2.6 - Four Disc Set! Rock-stable Performance (Unix), Apr. 1998 (Box 2)
- FreeBSD 3.0 Snapshot! (Unix), May 22, 1997 (Box 2)
  - 4.4BSD Lite, Jul. 1994 (Box 2)
- FreeBSD 3.1 - Four Disc Set! Rock-stable Performance (Unix), Mar. 1999 (Box 2)
  - CICA Shareware for Windows (Windows 95, 3.1), August 1996 (Box 2)
- FreeBSD 3.3 - Four Disc Set! Rock-Stable Performance! (Unix), Oct. 1999 (Box 2)
- FreeBSD 4.0 Four Disc Set! Rock-stable Performance! (Unix), Mar. 2000 (Box 2)
- FreeBSD 4.3 Four Disc Set! Rock-stable Performance! (Unix), Apr. 2001 (Box 2)
- FreeBSD 4.6 Four Disc Set! Rock-stable Performance! (Unix), Jun. 2002 (Box 2)
- FreeBSD 5.5 Four Disc Set - Rock-stable Performance! (Unix), Jun. 2006 (Box 2)
- CICA MicroSoft CDROM (Windows), Apr. 1993 (Box 1)
- CICA MSWindows CDROM (Windows), Nov. 1993 (Box 1)
- CICA for MSWINDOWS CD-ROM (Windows), Dec. 1993 (Box 1)
- CICA CDROM for MSWINDOWS (Windows), Apr. 1994 (Box 1)
- CICA Shareware for Windows (Windows), Sep. 1994 (Box 1)
- CICA Shareware for Windows (Windows), Feb. 1995 (Box 1)
- CICA Shareware for Windows (Windows 95, 3.1), Aug. 1995 (Box 2)
- CICA Shareware for Windows (Chinese Version) (Windows), Sep. 1995 (Box 2)
- CICA Shareware for Windows (Windows 95, 3.1), Mar. 1996 (Box 2)
- CICA Shareware für Windows (German version) (Windows), Jul. 1996 (Box 2)
- CICA Shareware per Windows (Italian version) (Windows 95, 3.1), Jul. 1996 (Box 2)
- CICA NT (Windows NT), Dec. 1996 (Box 2)
- CICA Shareware for Windows (Windows), Feb. 1997 (Box 1)
- CICA NT (Windows NT), Apr. 1997 (Box 2)
- CICA Shareware for Windows (Windows 95, 3.1), Aug. 1997 (Box 2)
- CICA NT (Windows NT), Nov. 1997 (Box 2)
- CICA 32: 32-Bit Applications - Four Disc Set! (Windows 95, 98, NT, HTML), Oct. 1999 (Box 2)
- CICA 32: 32-Bit Applications - Four Disc Set! (Windows 95, 98, NT, HTML), Mar. 2000 (Box 2)
- CICA 32: 32-Bit Applications - Four Disc Set! (Windows 95, 98, 2000, HTML), Aug. 2000 (Box 2)